Guide to the William Sulzer Papers 1860s?-1941 MS 607
New-York Historical Society
- Photographs, albums, postcards, mostly related to Alaska, circa 1904-1930s (Offsite-box 25)
  4 albums that hold primarily photographs of mostly Alaska. These are of landscapes, wildlife/animals (reindeer, walrus, malamutes, dog sled teams), Indigeneous peoples, miners, towns and buildings, mills, transportation (boats, Sulzer's bi-plane), etc. One album is inscribed as holding photos from a reconnaissance survey of the route of the Alaska Midland Railroad by John Rosene and engineers. The albums also hold clippings, maps, postcards,and brochures. One album that holds many postcards also includes some of the southwest United States. While much is undated, the bulk dated is from circa 1904-07 and 1924. The box also holds folders of loose, related photographs and postcards and a publicity booklet from the Alaska Industrial Company.
- Photographs of Sulzer, family, and other, 1800s-1930s (Offsite-box 26)
  This box holds portrait photographs, drawings, and engravings of Sulzer taken at various times of his life (many copies of several of these images); portrait photographs of Sulzer's grandparents, parents, siblings, and wife; images of Sulzer with groups and in various contexts (other than in connection with Alaska, which are in box 25); and miscellaneous other images. Also here is an original ticket to the U.S. Senate gallery for the trial of President Andrew Johnson in 1868.
- Lantern slides (glass) (Box 27)
  Many lantern slides of Alaska scenes and others of industrial settings and ship transportation. These latter scenes might be related to the Alaskan mining operations, though not of Alaska itself. There are also several lantern slides of political content that seem to have been used for Sulzer's gubernatorial campaign.
- Nitrate negatives (RESTRICTED; IN COLD STORAGE) (Folder MS607)
  Several negatives of snapshots from Alaska have been separated from the collection for cold storage. Special arrangements need to be made with reference@nyhistory.org to access these. Many of the negatives, though not necessarily all, have photographic prints in box 25.
- Letterbox (print matter and other), 1880s-1940 (Offsite-box 28)
  Original letterbox from Sulzer with booklets and pamphlets of historical speeches, recitations, works by Robert Ingersoll, and other literary and philosophical matters, with a few on foreign policy. Also holds several envelopes of clippings, labeled by topic, some with typescript of Sulzer's remarks, poetry, etc. connected to it.
- Letterbox (print matter), 1890s-1938 (Offsite-box 28)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with booklets and pamphlets: U.S. House of Representatives report on coal in Alaska for the Navy (1914); many copies of Sulzer's "Sayings of a Sourdough" published as #1757 in the Little Blue Book series by Haldeman-Julius Publications (1938); some Sulzer speeches (1890s); and additional copies of "Thus Spake a Man" and other political pamphlets of the American Party and others (circa 1916). Clippings and ephemera related to the American Party and Prohibition Party (platform, etc.).
- Letterbox (print matter), circa 1906-1941 (Offsite-box 28)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with booklets, clippings, and other print matter with his speeches, and Edgar L. Murlin's biographical piece. There are a few letters from Sulzer, including one to N-YHS regarding gifts he made to them and a letter to the University of Arizona informing President Alfred Atkinson that Sulzer had transfered ownership to the university of the Prince Albert Gold Mines (1941).
- Letterbox (print matter), 1880s-1910s (Offsite-box 29)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with pamphlets, booklets, and clippings on political matters, philosophical, and literary. Many, though not necessarily all, are found elsewhere in the collection.
- Letterbox (clippings), circa 1909 (Offsite-box 29)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer, mostly of clippings ("data") in envelopes by various topics, some with the typescript of Sulzer's remarks related to the clippings. Predominant in this box is the topic of "Lincoln" and relates to the 1909 centennial of his birth. There is a eulogy for Patrick Keenan of the Jefferson Club and several general matters (biographical, religious, etc.).
- Letterbox (print matter, clippings), 1890s-1920 (Offsite-box 30)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with clippings and pamphlets principally on the topic of "Money and the money trust," but also politics, including documents from the "Committee of 48" (1919-20), National Socialists, National Party, American Party, and the Democratic and Republican parties.
- Letterbox (print matter, clippings), 1880s-1920s (Offsite-box 30)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with clippings in envelopes by topic, with some related typescripts of Sulzer's remarks. Principal topics here are Alaska, George Washington, Irish patriotism, Robert Burns, Lincoln. There are also booklets, clippings and other print matter on the Bahai Faith (or Bahaism as used in the collection).
- Letterbox (clippings), 1920s (Offsite-box 31)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with loose clippings. The box label indicates these are political, biographical, and literary.
- Letterbox (clippings), 1930s (Offsite-box 31)
  Original letterbox of Sulzer with loose clippings.
- Wood blocks, undated (Offsite-box 32)
  Most, though not all, appear to be images of Sulzer. There is a small wood block for printing the American Party's Liberty Bell symbol.
- Wood blocks, undated (Offsite-box 33)
  These appear to be all images of Sulzer.
- Correspondence. Oversize, 1932 (Offsite-box 34)
  4 items mounted on board: 2 letters to Sulzer from Cornell University Library acknowledging donations of books and documents, a clipping of "Mr. Sulzer's rules of life," and a photo of Sulzer at the Abraham Clark monument.
- Correspondence. Oversize, 1920-1934 (Offsite-box 35)
  Holds 3 montages on board: 1) Letters from Cornell University Library acknowledging donations of books, etc., photos of Sulzer at his plane in Alaska, and clippings; 2) image from the New York Herald Tribune of the Graf Zeppelin arriving at Washington, DC, with postcards related to the voyage, in German (1928); and 3) letter from Abdul Baha Abbas, in Arabic with English translation on Committee on Foreign Affairs letterhead (1920).
- Clippings. Oversize, 1903-1909 (Offsite-box 34)
  4 newspaper articles mounted on board: Sulzer mother's ownership of an old bible (1903), "Hebrew Standard" re: Sulzer support for Russia's Jews (1904), "The Argus" political support for Sulzer (1908), and "The Tammany Times" re: Sulzer support for an income tax (1909).
- Clippings. Oversize, 1904, 1909 (Offsite-box 35)
  2 clippings on board: full sheet from the Batavia Times reporting on a banquet for Sulzer (1904) and an article from "Cronista" of Guatemala about Sulzer, in Spanish (1909)
- Photographs. Oversize, circa 1913-1930s (Offsite-box 34)
  Some of the photos in this box are larger, or mounted, prints of those in boxes 25 and 26. Photos here include Sulzer greeting José Cipriano Castro Ruiz of Venezuela (1913?), mounted Alaska photos (1930s), Sulzer in his office (undated), Masonic dinner at the Hotel McAlpin (1932), testimonial dinner held for Sulzer by the Mason's Republic Lodge (1936), and photo of an Asian gentleman (Jong Sning?) inscribed to Sulzer (undated).
- Political cartoons/caricatures. Oversize, circa 1904-1913 (Offsite-box 34)
  15 original drawings by Simons(?), L.W. Ford, Rollin Kirby, W.A. Rogers, Denys Wortman, Marcus, George Washington Rehse, Homer Davenport, ZAZ, F.M. Walts, Woodson, and others. Some inscribed.
- Political cartoons/caricatures. Oversize, circa 1906-1913 (Offsite-box 35)
  12 original drawings by George Washington Rehse, Homer Davenport, L.W. Ford, W. Starrett, J. Norman Lynd, C.R. Macauley, Bernard Corvinus, Berryman.
- Certificates. Oversize, 1905-1913 (Offsite-box 35)
  7 certificates on boards: commemorative diploma for valuable services from the Lewis and Clark Centennial American Pacific Exposition and Oriental Fair (1905); life membership in Pioneers of Alaska, Igloo #1 (1907); acknowledgement of oration at the Fraternal Order of Eagles, Scranton, Pa. (1908); Grand Prize ribbon and certificate awarded to the Alaska Industrial Company of Sulzer, Alaska, for its exhibit of a reproduction of a copper mine at the Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition in Seattle (1909); election to governor (1912); congratulatory greetings from the inmates, warden and superintendent of Clinton Prison (1913); and acknowledgement from Equity Congress of Sulzer's signing of the "Colored Regiment Bill" forming a Black state militia unit (1913).
- Presidential pen & related documents, 1910 (Offsite-box 35)
  Mounted items: the pen used by President William Taft to sign the bill authorizing the salvage of the U.S.S. Maine, with the letter from the White House conveying the pen to Sulzer, Sulzer's comments in support of the legislation, and the article from the newspaper "Democracy" about the bill.